[Music]
this
hello hello good evening good day
everybody great to be back on the 86th
live stream
and as you know today is a live video
chat session so i'm going to be inviting
you all to come and ask me questions on
the broadcast so let me share the link
for joining
let me share the link let me do it right
away
let's see where is it oh there you go i
think i have shared the link
and
not sure if it's visible
one second
just give me a second
yes i think i should be able to share it
now
here we are
that should be
we should do it uh let me pin the
message
so everyone can see it yes there it is
it's visible now
so i am looking forward to you guys
girls ladies gentlemen all of you
joining ah here we go everyone's joining
fantastic
okay i can see lots of people have
joined
already that's good that's good so let
us let us get going and i will
ah
there we go
okay so whom shall we bring in first
let's bring in mr sahil kumar
hello
hello sir can you hear me
yes i can hear you how are you doing
so that i have a doubt sir
how to remember physics formulas
how to remember physics formula so
that's the question good question
you remember physics formulas and you
remember physics the laws of physics by
doing a lot of practice so you take an
equation which is a physical formula and
you solve a lot of problems using that
formula
like not 10 20 maybe 100 200 it takes
time if you do that amount of practice
then you will never be able to forget it
so it's all about practice practice
practice see there are two two ways of
learning something
one way is you read read read but then
you will forget 90 of it but if you take
the concepts and apply them by solving
problems then you will never forget it
so that is the correct way to learn
physics formulas and to learn the laws
of physics
does it make sense
yes sir
go it sir all the best
thank you sir
thank you thank you nice to meet you bye
okay i think i should ask everyone where
they are from okay let's do that
hello
uh good evening sir
good evening sir where are you from
what's your name
i am sharina
where are you from
i am from maharashtra
maharashtra all right sir what's your
question
sir my question was why did brahma
decline as a script to write indian
languages
in the medieval era
why did the script brahmi the brahma
script decline
see the brahmi script was prevalent when
was it prevalent more than two thousand
years ago
uh there were two scripts uh around that
time two two and a half thousand years
before today kharoshi and brahmay so
brahmi seems to have emerged out of the
old saraswati hindu script the indus
valley script they call it
and the thing is that you know when you
are talking about a time period of
centuries or thousands of years things
change things change so there is
evolution so brahmi gave rise to other
scripts and it's always evolution
languages change and evolve and even
scripts change and evolve culture also
changes and evolve everything changes
so if you're talking about a time period
of two and a half thousand years you're
gonna see changes so new versions of the
script will come up and then you had
periscopes like the sharda script and
eventually you had the dev nag you have
the maharashtrik
maharashtra script and various other
grantha script lots of scripts emerged
out of older scripts that's just the way
the world works if you're talking about
just five years of ten years you will
not see that happening but if you look
at the time period of two thousand two
and a half thousand years you will see
old things going obsolete and new things
emerging in that place so it's just a
natural
phenomenon it's evolution evolution
happens even in culture and
in society so that's why brahmi
eventually went out of use
and other scripts replaced it
all right thank you sir thank you
nice meeting you nice meeting you all
the best bye thank you
okay whom shall we bring in now
let's bring in mr hardik
hello hello
how similar are
they right why has mr gandhi been
compared with martin luther king and
nelson mandela
see
it's all about image building it's about
creating a certain image it's all about
marketing so the way certain leaders are
marketed it all creates it creates a
certain kind of image
so uh if you have been watching what i
have been saying over the past few
months it's
if you look at mr gandhi mr gandhi and
his life and his career and his writings
objectively you will see that he is a
certain kind of
historical figure but the way he has
been portrayed is very different from
what he actually was like so he has been
portrayed as a saintly person as on the
same level as the great mahatmas of the
old times like mahatma buddha etc which
actually is not quite accurate he was
actually a politician and a very very
good politician at that he was able to
out maneuver people like swabasha and
the rebels and get them ejected from the
congress party
by political maneuvering and so on so mr
gandhi actually was not the way he is
portrayed now um
the thing is this in in other countries
they have wholesale uh bought into the
image that has been created of mr gandhi
and therefore people like mr martin
luther king who were fighting for civil
rights in the u.s they looked upon mr
gandhi as an inspiration as somebody who
apparently
uh
got rid of the british from india
without resorting to violence so so that
is the kind of uh image that was created
and that's why people like mr martin
luther king who was not a historian
that's why they they are
so mr gandhi as an inspiration i mean mr
martin luther king was fighting a big
struggle for civil rights for the for
the african-american people he didn't
have the time to go and look at history
study history study mr gandhi's writings
he just saw him as a big inspirational
figure and so that's that's why there is
this comparison that has been drawn even
mr mandela
eventually he became i mean see mr
mandela was jailed by the south africans
and the reason he was jailed for 27 or
so years is because he was initially
because because he had resorted to
violence in order to try and get rid of
the apartheid regime so mr mandela
eventually disavowed violence and that's
why he's also
compared with mr gandhi especially after
mr mandela was released and he became
this pacifistic figure he emphasized
forgiveness and reconciliation and all
that which is good i have nothing
against that that was a very noble
gesture on mr k mr mandela's part and it
ensured that south african society went
on peacefully more or less so that's the
reason why these three historical
figures are kind of compared
but i think india needs to revisit mr
gandhi's legacy and look at it look at
his life and career from a more
objective lens that would be good for
the national interest
all right thank you nice meeting you
okay whom shall we bring in
um
let us bring in mr shane kurian
good evening sir
hello
hello how are you
i'm very well sir how are you where are
you from
i'm from uh kerala
and uh
uh
i i i want to ask you a question the
question is
that um
about uh faster than live faster
faster than light travel
okay
uh
what what other what what types do you
think is the
uh
appropriate faster than light travel to
the stars
and do you think
quantum teleportation is an effective
means of uh
effective uh faster than light travel
uh technology do you think uh
quantum teleportation is a
better technology if
if human beings
manage to achieve it
right so the the concept of faster than
light travel is not allowed according to
the laws of physics the speed limit the
universal speed limit is the speed of
light nothing can ever go
past that nothing no massive object can
even reach the speed of light because
there is something called uh
so so as as your speed as your velocity
increases as it reaches relativistic
speeds closer to the speed of light your
mass also increases
and uh if you if your massive object
even if it is an electron even even if
it's if even if it's a proton if it were
to reach the speed of light its mass
would become infinite
and therefore according to the laws of
physics according to special relativity
the equations are pretty straightforward
and the derivations are pretty
straightforward according to this it's
simply not possible
to uh to travel at the speed of light
what about
what about being quant
what about being quantum teleported to
other
exoplanets
yeah quantum teleportation is a theory
and it's not quite about transporting
a person a from point a to point b it's
it's a it's the the name is actually
quite misleading so it it won't work and
quantum mechanics actually it only
applies to
ultra microscopic sub atomic particles
it cannot apply i cannot
i am not a quantum object you are not a
quantum object we are macroscopic object
and our bodies in our world it obeys the
laws of classical physics not quantum
physics so quantum technologies when we
talk about them they are still quite a
bit in in the realm of science fiction
we of course do use quantum mechanics in
uh various
technologies like telecommunications
semiconductors and all that but
teleportation is still in the realm of
science fiction the only uh
and
what i can also offer is also within
science fiction it's about going through
a wormhole
which i mean we have never actually seen
a verbal but it's allowed i mean verbal
solutions do exist in einstein's
equations of general relativity so that
may be a possibility and there's also
the warp drive thing that's going on so
it's all still very much theoretical if
it ever happens it will happen 100 200
years down the line perhaps possibly but
as of today it's it's all within the
realm of science fiction and imagination
it's not possible as of today i'm sorry
to disappoint you but i have to give you
a realistic answer so that's where we
are
okay thank you sir
nice meeting you sir all the best
okay
let's bring in mr udit
hello
yes sir hello sir how are you how are
you doing sir
i am very well how are you doing where
are you from
um i'm from saudi arabia i was there the
last session too so oh you were the last
time okay yes sir so my question is from
the current affairs right now we got the
news about the abg shaping company right
about the fraud and everything so we
keep on hearing like major frauds
happening in our country from the
banking system and all and like people
like harshad mehta used the loopholes
and everything and many people like
vijay mali and nirav modi sir so do you
think or do you know anything about
these loopholes or what were then what
caused
such frauds to happen so
uh
i am not aware of the actual details and
all that of these things but what i can
tell you is that in the indian system
has unfortunately for the past seven
plus decades relied on corruption on
underhand deals i'm not saying all of it
is corrupt but there is obviously we
know it it's all been reported it's not
like some some big revelation there's
been a lot of corruption and that's just
the way the system was run for decades
and that's why you had these things
happening it's called crony capitalism
the ruling party the ruling regime will
go hand in hand with various business
people and they will have a various
deals i am not pointing fingers at any
specific individual or or anything like
that i'm just saying typically that's
how these things happen i'm not saying
it was everywhere but yeah it was there
like you give the example of rashad
mehta so obviously he could have he
could not have done all that without
without other people knowing about it
and other people also benefiting from it
so those who are in power typically
benefit from such things typically not
always
i'm not sure about the details yes sir
but that's how it is so what needs to
happen in india is we need proper
regulation we need to clean up the
system and i think that is happening
right now the more the system is
formalized the more the economy economy
is formalized and regulated the less you
will have less corruption you're gonna
have so that is the direction we are
going in actually uh about five years
ago more than 50 of the economy was
informal so it was completely untaxed
and it was essentially corruption you
could call it corruption in some in most
cases i suppose yes but to be i think
around 10 of the economy only is today
informal the rest of it is all
formalized and so on so we are going in
the right direction but still there's a
lot of cleanup that needs to happen not
out about that but yes
the thing is i i am optimistic because
i'm seeing the right moves being made
and we are progressing in the correct
way so that's what i can say so within
this question only i'm not already
adding another question i'm sticking to
the one question only sir so but when we
talk about the loophole sir
yes like how do we get to know about the
loopholes that like which they use we
don't get to know about it their
loophole is not supposed to be known we
are not supposed to know about them i
don't know any specific loopholes i can
just see there are low poles because
these things happen
yes sir okay it's only insiders
who will know
and be able to pinpoint the loopholes
yes i am not an economist i am not into
banking so and i am a scientist so i i
really cannot give you a specific
decision
okay thank you bye
all right uh let us oh my goodness we
have our good old friend bhanu
hello sir
good evening sir
good evening we meet again
so you're from jammu right
yes sir yes sir yeah what's the question
sir recently mr putin said that if nato
country will interfere in the matter of
ukraine
they might use uh nuclear weapons
sir what will be the impact of this on
the world as well as india and sir how
much chances of world war
okay let's talk about nuclear weapons
yes mr putin did allude to nuclear
weapons he said that russia has a
nuclear weapons power so don't mess with
us that's what i said
uh in my opinion the probability of the
use of nuclear weapons is
zero
nobody
is going to use nuclear weapons it's not
something you use it's something you
keep with yourself as a deterrent
it's only something you use as the
absolute last option
so nuclear weapons are not something
that are to be used it's only something
you keep for
uh deterrence so i don't think there's
any any possibility
of
nuclear weapons being used in any
conflict that arises unless certain
thresholds are crossed and i don't think
anybody is crazy enough to cross through
those thresholds so what mr putin
said is called a nuclear saber rattling
just talk about nuclear weapons and so
on just to keep other people in place
and remind them that i am strong enough
and i can defend myself so that's what's
happening now what's happening in
ukraine
uh the american media the western media
is right now saying that there's going
to be a war next week there's going to
be war and that sort of thing there's
going to be invasion there's going to be
a russian invasion of ukraine in the
next four to five days in the next week
at most that's what they are claiming as
if they are able to read the mind of mr
putin and they are aware of everything
that he is planning i mean who are they
to say that on what basis are they
making the claim
anyway we will see how things escalate
how things uh play out to be but i do
not see any possibility of nuclear war
whatsoever if there is an invasion of
ukraine it will be very well calculated
and calibrated mr putin also doesn't
want to be faced with a big proper nato
big
war with nato on his western front so
it's all about calculations it's all
about what is your national national
interest on your objectives the thing is
that russia feels that it is being
encircled by nato and it is not a
misplaced feeling because if you look at
the maps they are being encircled by
nato and nato is trying to now uh
uh
move into ukraine essentially they want
ukraine to become part of their or part
of their orbit and that is obviously a
red line that mr putin will not allow
them to cross so that is in short what
the conflict is but the whenever when we
talk about nuclear weapons there is no
probability of them being used
all right sir
thank you sir thank you nice to meet you
all right
let us bring in
uh
whom shall i bring in let us bring in mr
rishab singh
hello
hello so am i uh audible
yes sir
where are you from
so uh i'm from norada up
okay
as i think we have met in a last i think
in the last meet
okay okay
so so my question is uh so it's on the
burka recently we have a burkha
controversy ongoing in india so can you
shed some
light on the origin of the burkha that
how did it originated and why
most of the muslim women are so obvious
with wearing the burkha and so the next
part of the question is uh i've read
somebody in indonesia
uh earlier in back in 40s and 50s women
didn't used to wear the burkha but then
after due to the
arabic influence because arab exports
some oil in these countries the usage of
burka increased so so what's on you
what's your views on it
uh i must apologize to you because i am
not an expert in these matters it is
something that i have never really
studied or you know the history of the
uh this this government or or even of
this culture it is not something that i
am
uh anyway
an expert in so if i were to make some
statements it could be wrong and i don't
want that to happen
so therefore i am not the right person
to ask these questions all right there
are many other experts and there are
many other channels that discuss this in
great detail so maybe you could look
there
but i can offer you one more question
instead of this please ask me something
else and i'll answer that
okay okay so so uh
i'm i was thinking i've read somewhere
that most of the muslim dynasties even
in india they were very obvious with the
persian culture
even when mughals came to india why they
didn't adopted indian culture because
even indian culture was also ancient
like persian and they even didn't
adopted the roman and greek culture why
was it so obvious with the persian
culture what was so special about it
i think what happened is that see when
you talk about the so-called mughals who
are actually timurids they're actually
the turks
when they came to india so it all starts
with this fellow called what's the name
babar zahiruddin babar he was a kind of
a loser so he lost and then there was
his son humayun he also lost to share
shah sorry he had to go into exile in
persia
so humayun i believe went into exile
escaped with just ran for his life went
to persia took asylum there he had to be
he he was forced to convert to shia
islam and then eventually he came back
to india after shah suri died
and
and yes something like that i think was
it humayun was it akbar i think it was
humayun who came back to india
and he came with a whole retinue
yes
so it was
it was mine yes so he came to india from
persia with the whole retinue of persian
officials
and uh when he was able to regain the
throne he installed all this persian
officials etc as his bureaucrats and
administrators so that's why persian
became this the court language of the
turkic uh
kingdom the so-called mughal empire
because they had all these uh persian
officials who did all the accounting all
the administration and all that and it
just carried on from the time onwards
from from humayun to akbar to whatever
their descendants were so that's how
come that that's how persian became the
court language and that's why there was
so much influence of persian culture and
language among
these dynasties these foreign dynasties
right thank you sir thank you so much
okay let's uh bring in somebody else
let's bring in mr sahas
hello
hello sir are you able to hear me
i am able to hear you where are you from
sir
sir i am from uttar pradesh
that's a question
i said more than a question i want your
perspective on it sir through social
media it's even more visible that there
are people in this country who have this
innate devilish hatred towards this
country and towards the hindu community
and these people are present across
communities even the hindu community
so my question is how is the state of
bharat which is highly developed and
highly civilized but it's also
culturally connected to its roots how is
that state possible when you have n
number of institutional powers working
to
break or destroy that very basic india
idea of india
all right so this is the question i have
addressed multiple times but of course
it's a good question so let's take it
again so what social media is doing so
many people say that social media is
polarizing the country right lots of
people say it's causing polarization
it's causing the outpouring of hatred
and all that
that's one perspective the other
perspective is that social media is
simply showing the attitudes that
already exist in the country it's simply
showing that right
and now when you talk about the the what
what is called the breaking india forces
all the various ngos and various other
organizations etc that are essentially
working and against india's national
interest well uh
that is because of foreign influence in
india there's a lot of foreign funding
that that is pouring into india from
various from a variety of
foreign external sources there are so
many ngos that work in india officially
and they they also worked as work as
conduits for foreign interference in
india so that is the situation exists
today
this situation exists because india is
currently not powerful or not enough to
stand up to certain very powerful
foreign forces india is not a superpower
india is merely a middle power at best
india is merely a regional power at best
india's economy is about three trillion
dollars of gdp right
it's not even 10 trillion trillion
dollars it's nowhere comparable to the
real big powers in the world and that's
why they are able as of today to arm
twist india and they are completely
capable of destroying their india if
they want so the government whether we
like it or not has to strike a certain
balance so what needs to happen right
now is india needs to bide its time and
work as hard as possible over the next
10 20 years to grow its economy at least
10 percent a year anyhow until it is at
least 10 trillion dollars in in value
once that happens india will be entirely
different beast
if you look at china when it was a 3
trillion economy it was very it was a
very modest country they did not have
this wolf warrior diplomacy all this
aggressive nature nothing they used to
be they used to keep quiet they used to
swallow on the all the insults the west
were throwing at them and they just
worked quietly so that's what india
needs to do
once india becomes a more powerful
country all of this will be taken care
of so what needs to happen what we need
to do is reach that state as fast as
possible that's what needs to happen so
that's what i can offer you
sir is this one of the reason why you
say that hinduism can eradicate can be
eradicated in the next 50 years
yeah if india doesn't take care of the
economy and all that see that's why
economy is very important as your
economy grows military also grows then
you can deal with things if that doesn't
happen yeah indian culture will
disappear in the next 50 or 50 to 100
years certainly hinduism like you say
yeah
okay thank you sir thank you so it's all
in our hands yes thank you thank you
nice meeting you
all right
all right let's bring in mr
mr kebat
hello
hello sir namaskar
namaste
i can hear you sir where are you from
yeah
i'm from mumbai
and
my question has
it's kind of dark in its subject matter
but anyway we need to have these
discussions
um and i have to ask you about
jogendranath mandal
the first i think he was the law
minister of pakistan
was a first law minister
and the consequences that uh or the
circumstances that led to his
departure from pakistan from his post
and then he fled to india to bengal
and he died over there so the horrific
atrocities that he saw
in pakistan on the minority community
over there
which led to his departure from pakistan
also
if uh you know
if you could throw some light on the
bangladesh liberation war
and the
exclusively on the atrocities on women
because this is something that
we need to talk about we need to discuss
it's a very grizzly and horrifying
chapter of
south asian history so could you talk
about that 1971 bangladesh war
the atrocities okay when you talk about
that okay so when you speak about
jughead
was he from east
was he pakistan there
uh he was a dalit leader
who
sort of fled when he went to
west pakistan the modern day pakistan
and
he was so filled with you know hate for
the hindu community so he decided to
just leave india go to pakistan
okay
you know
yeah obviously if you if you are in
pakistan you will see all kinds of
atrocities we know that when pakistan
was formed
the hindu population i mean non-muslim
population was around 30 i'm not sure
what the exact percentage was but today
it's less than two percent so obviously
something happened right
so so that's just the the history now i
am not once again an expert in the
horrific atrocities that happened in the
1971 war i have seen some pictures etc
when i was a kid i have not studied that
because it is something that
it it's not fun to study
it's not fun to read so i have not read
it i would not be able to give you the
details of what exactly happened i know
that millions of people were massacred
the official figures are like 1.5
million obviously that's been that's an
under representation of what really must
have happened and obviously it is the
hindus that would have who would have
been targeted and i'm aware of the kind
of
i mean i've
heard about the kind of atrocities that
were provided especially on women but i
don't have exact statistics i have not
read the details but of course it all
happened it's kind of being whitewashed
now
so that's just the way the narratives
are built even in bangladesh they've
tried they've kind of forgotten and if
you see the attitudes today among the
bangladeshi people they are like very
much pro pakistan modern pro india so
it's all about what kind of history they
are taught and what kind of political
environment there is and what the media
tells you that's what you swallow
wholesale and that's how attitudes are
formed so surprisingly today in
bangladesh you will see a very strong
anti-india attitude among most people
it's like they have forgotten what
happened in 71 and how india saved them
from from what the pakistanis were doing
that's just the way it is so that's what
i can tell you sir well it is quite
disheartening to see the attitudes of
bangladeshi youth yes towards india
right now yes
yeah true but it i would appreciate it
greatly if you know you threw some light
or you made a video make of the
bangladesh liberation war because it is
something that is not talked about at
all
because you know it's so uh
it kind of
completely
it's brushed on the carpet and it's
again
please i agree
certainly thank you for the suggestion i
will i will
take it into consideration thank you
thanks a lot thank you nice meeting you
bye
okay let us bring in mr shreesh
hello
hello sir i'm a big fan of yourself sir
you are a great mentor to me
thank you so much thank you so much very
good
sir i am from delhi
yes sir
yes sir sir my question was that sir in
one of your videos or it was a session i
i don't remember so you said that
currently in india india does not have
any influence in any other countries
and so you gave the examples like
in
thailand india has zero influence there
so sir but there are many organizations
like iskcon which are spreading indian
culture worldwide so sir what is your
take on this
so what i was talking about is hard
power there are two kinds of power
the real power is hard power down india
is obsessed with soft power culture and
all that but if you see
india is not even doing anything to
spread its soft power its culture of
course organizations like iskcon exist
and they are
present mostly in the west i believe in
the western world
in europe in north america maybe some
other countries also i'm not aware so uh
i was talking about soft power when it i
was talking about hard power i mean now
when it comes to culture cultural
influence there is
a component of soft power you will find
a lot of uh
remnants of indian culture in southeast
asia in thailand in burma in vietnam in
laos etc in indonesia and all the way up
to japan you will still see that but
today india is no longer looked upon as
a country that
the kind of respect the people had in
the past for india has kind of
evaporated because of what's happened uh
in the past thousand years especially
what's happened after independence in
india did not come up bring itself out
of poverty quickly india
under the narrowband regime kind of
enjoyed remaining in poverty and so on
so
so when it comes to uh software you are
talking about soft power we can do so
much more we can do so much more uh
our film industry can become a veritable
force from the soft power perspective
but you see that but what we find is
that bollywood doesn't even represent
indian culture it represents god knows
what culture
what you see in bollywood whether it's
the films the songs or the dances that
is not indian culture it is something
absurd and something something
yeah so bollywood unfortunately what it
should be doing it's not doing and india
doesn't have an independent music
industry of its own and so on so india
can do so much more from the perspective
of soft power look at look at japan
they have this anime industry enemy
industry japanese anime is a huge
cultural force globally
i mean kids youngsters teenagers they
they are they worship although japanese
enemy and they don't watch it yes
yeah and similarly for other things like
south korea the bts or whatever boy
bands etc they have girl bands also so
these this is what soft power is in
india is not currently as of today not
doing much once india rises economy
economically it's going to happen but i
was talking about hard power that is the
real power your soft power is useless
unless you have hard power to back it up
yes sir yes sir thank you so much sir
bye
thank you
okay let's bring in somebody else
let's bring in mr khushel
hello
my question is uh where are you from
where are you from hello hyderabad
hyderabad hyderabad all right all right
all right nice meeting you
yeah uh so nice to meet you too uh yes
uh in seventh century uh there was this
thing called impalement of jains in
madurai
i don't know if it's true or not but
they call it a genocide of eight
thousand jain monks there
okay
is it true sir like a lot of people deny
it i haven't i i have i haven't come
across this i haven't studied this i
haven't read this if it
i don't know where these narratives come
from and if some 8 000 people are killed
is it a genocide in chittorgarh akbar
killed 30 000 men women and children
it's not called a genocide it's simply
brushed under the carpet but if 8 000
people i'm not even sure if that
happened but how come there is a
genocide how can they i'm not pointing
figures at you the historians or whoever
it is that has portrayed this event
which i am not sure even if it even
happened but if it happened how can you
call that a genocide it's a massacre
and you know if you look at the global
history
world history you will see such events
happening all the time but if it happens
in india it's somehow a blot on the
culture of india so that's the kind of
portrayal that happens
in
by by these
indian court historians durbari
historians marxist historians and so on
so to answer your specific question i am
not sure i have not come across this
incident i have heard people allude to
it and he's gone
okay so i hope that answers that
question
uh right let's bring in somebody else
whom shall i bring in
whom shall i bring let us bring in mr
vibin
hello
hi sir hi hi where are you from sir i'm
from chennai
chennai all right sir what's your
question
your opinion on xiaomi reconnaissance
swami vivekananda all right see um
once again i'm getting all these tough
questions today see i haven't studied mr
swami swami vivekananda i haven't
studied his works i haven't read his
whatever he's written so i i i still
don't know much about him unfortunately
obviously he's revered in india there
must be a reason why he is revered but i
personally have never studied his works
i have not read his writings
i have not heard his speeches i only
know that people worship him so that's
all i can offer you unfortunately i am
not an authority on the works and the
right in the life and the career of
swami vivekananda so unfortunately i
don't have much of an opinion because i
am not informed well informed enough
okay thank you all right anyway thanks
and nice meeting you
okay whom shall we bring in let's bring
in mr ronesh
hello
hi sir can you hear me
i can hear you sir i have i met you
before yes yes uh i have been in one of
the other shows yeah
okay can you remind me where you're from
i'm i'm from delhi but currently i'm
right now i'm in canada
canada all right so all right okay nice
meeting you again and what's your
question
okay so
this question kind of popped up with one
of my discussion with my friend so it
just at a random day so i was just uh
just telling him that how uh how great
our culture was how much knowledge we
possess and all but then he gave me a
very pointing reply that if we were so
great if we had so much
vast knowledge all over the students
from all over the world so we used to be
us of that time right so they were
coming us to acquire knowledge so he
just told me very simple and
apply that then why we were why we did
not utilize that knowledge so as the
great britain did all the entire europe
did so out of industry regular
revolution so why we
so were we just simply sitting on that
knowledge or not implementing it because
we heard that we had so much
medical enhancement surgeries were
happening and and astronomy there must
be so much so what really happened that
and i also kind of observed this this is
our some of our indian tendencies so we
have power both soft power and physical
and the hard power as we were just
saying but we do not exert it but so why
is this some sort of a thing in indian
mentality or something so even if you
see it in the current time so
for example the indian day of parasol in
the us so they are the top ceos and all
but if you see in the hollywood movies
or anything so we have so much
misrepresentation no one takes us that
of a serious power as compared to china
or japan
and even coming about the hard power so
even in the times that like uh we we did
not attack even the aggressor like
pakistan they have attacked us
first
but uh but even when we just stopped at
that line that uh what do you call uh
the kashmir lacy but we could very well
take what was really ours but even
i get it i get it there are lots of
examples yeah yeah so let me yeah it's a
very good question it's a very good
question so you said that india was the
u.s of the old days right that's what
you said i disagree i disagree the us
whether you realize it or not whether we
realize it realize it or not the u.s is
an imperial power
it's an empire it's a global empire
we may not call it an empire today
but it is a global empire look at that
and see where their military bases are
their military bases are spread all
across the world
they have the ability to intervene
militarily anywhere in the world at 30
minutes notice
they control the global systems their
currency is the world's reserve currency
they are an imperial hegemonic power
it's a class it's a classical example of
an imperial hegemonic power that's what
the u.s is india was never that it was
never part of indian culture so even
when we had grand unified empire like
the mauryan empire or the kushan empire
or various other empires later on like
the maratha empire we were never
hegemonic and we were we never had this
exclusivist supremacist culture
and of course india's economy was over
one-third of the entire world's gdp yeah
because we were completely totally
industrialized we were the world's first
industrialized civilization but we did
not use it to go and invade other
countries the thoughts apparently never
occurred to us right so what we had is
we had very high standards of living we
had a very good uh
we had all these industries we had
healthcare we had all that public works
and all that but we were never it's
about the culture and the attitude we
never wanted to steal from others we
never wanted to destroy other countries
and transfer all the wealth from there
into india so that is the attitude india
never had these other countries which we
talk about the last 500 years the age of
colonization the european countries only
wanted one thing destroy others and
transfer the wealth there
that attitude never was there in india
or in any dharmic country look at the
mongols look at the samurais look at all
the other asian empires kingdoms when
even when they were great they never
pillaged other countries they never
invaded other countries with the
objective of taking all the wealth
right
when when you look at the history of
japan it's only in the late 19th century
that the attitude changes and they try
to eradicate dharma and buddhism and the
meiji restoration happens and then you
see the horrific atrocities the japanese
perpetrated in china and elsewhere
because they abandoned those principles
so india
has never been a hegemonic power it has
been very powerful at times it has
always been an enormously powerful
economy but it has never been a
hegemonic threatening nation and that's
why we never did that we could have
invaded persia if we wanted we could
have invaded central asia if we wanted
we could have even the cholas even did
that they they invaded and uh they
invaded and conquered much of southeast
asia all the way to the philippines but
they never transferred the wealth from
there into india they actually enriched
the those places so it's all about the
culture the civilizational ethos and
values which is different when it comes
to india but now obviously we have to be
educated that this is the way the world
works the world is very different and we
have to ensure it never happens again
never again like the jews say
but do you see this happening because i
still see it's happening it's happening
slowly we are thinking we are seeing a
change in the mindset of india we have
nuclear weapons now yeah we have that
that uh
insurance
and obviously we are we are right now
what we india is doing is we are
following the maximum of ding shopping
means
stay quiet keep your head down bide your
time and work very hard and wait until
the time is right for until your economy
and military is powerful enough so
that's what i see happening it's going
to take another 10 20 years hopefully
but
we will rise again
and said that you are also doing a very
good job because i am seeing a very uh
very very young viewer so like you are
really giving them a lot of perspective
and good knowledge and one humble
suggestion if i can make a visit sir so
that would be uh sometime i follow our
channel a lot so we see those small
snippets of information for that
that why india had never invaded foreign
countries and all but it but
to draw a more conclusive uh knowledge
it would be good that if you just in
some of those sessions you pick a
particular topic and expand on it and
all that what that was mission
information so it could be india's
freedom moment or the role of india in
world war ii an entire topic rather than
fragmented knowledge because it would
really build up on having an uh that
what we know what was hidden from us so
that will be really great so if you can
do that in the future
thank you thank you for the suggestion
and nice meeting you again okay thank
you again sir okay see you thank you bye
okay
let us bring in somebody else
let us bring in mr uh
let's bring in mr sia bihari saran
hello
hello sir can you hear me hi
i can hear you sir where are you from
i'm from tokyo sir i'm i'm basically
from delhi yes but i'm in tokyo
nice to meet you too so my quick one
question is uh about the swastika symbol
um because recently i saw a documentary
where it
basically just
uh
opened it up that swastika was
it was not swastika it was a hooked
cross
but the name swastika was given to it
because of
you know demeaning the
the vedic culture what is your take on
that
i totally agree with this assessment the
uh
see in europe for instance first of all
let's talk about the swastika what it is
it's a very ancient very ancient
auspicial auspicious symbol
you find it in in india in the saraswati
valley region the
region harappan era etc it's uh you can
find so lots of
examples of swastika swastikas that you
find in the archaeological record
hundreds of them and these are like
around 5000 or so years old
and if we look deeper you may find even
older spasticas in india so in india the
record archaeological record shows that
it's at least 5000 years ago it was it
was re used as an auspicious symbol in
other parts of the world also you find
it i believe the oldest swastika-like
symbol was found in central europe
present-day ukraine it's a it's an ivory
carving of a bird which has swastika
like
carvings on it
and it's found all across the world it's
found in africa it's found in the native
american cultures it's a universal
symbol of positivity and auspiciousness
that's what the swastika is so it's not
something that is only restricted to
india but of course in the 20th and 21st
century the use went out i mean most of
the world more or less stopped using it
and it's only in the dharmic culture
that you find it so you're in tokyo if
you look at if you go to google maps and
you go to the city of tokyo or kyoto and
you search for temple it will be
represented by swastika right even today
in google maps yes yes because i i
remember when i went to near the tokyo
tower there is a very
huge temple and when i first saw a
swastika symbol there i it gave me a
goosebump because it was not indian
swastika but it was kind of the swastika
that you know hitler uh used in his flag
so i was kind of confused
that
you know is it just
what
no it is it is a very very auspicious
symbol in in the dharmic uh cultures in
all the dharmic cultures whether you
hinduism buddhism jainism whatever right
so you find the swastika in mongolia in
china in southeast asia in korea and in
japan also typically it's the inverted
swastika the river swastika in buddhism
right so it is a symbol of tantra etc
and all that so there's a whole story
behind it but you will also find it
throughout asia and other places now
what happened is when these in europe
they never called it the swastika they
called it the fifa the ghanaian the
hakken croix et cetera in german they
called it the hacking cruise the hooked
cross
so the germans never used the word
swastika for this symbol
and when hitler took uh misappropriated
it and used it for his political
purposes he called it the hakken kroitz
not the swastika but after the second
world war was over and the nazis were
defeated
the western writers started using the
hindu the sanskrit term swastika for the
hack and kreutz the hakken crutch is one
very specific misrepresentation of this
symbol it doesn't apply to everything
else so what the nazis did was they
stole the symbol and they used it for
something evil
and then
the western historians applied the
sanskrit term retrospectively
retroactively to this evil
symbol of nazism and that's why today
you can't use the swastika anywhere in
the world and if you talk about it
you're evil and you're not seeing all
that that sort of nonsense needs to end
we need to reclaim the swastika and we
need to impress upon the world that the
symbol the nazis used was the hooked
cross the hakken crutch not the swastika
the swastika is a symbol of
auspiciousness and positivity so that's
what the world needs to be told and we
need to do that
i know i have crossed my one question
limit but how do you think that we can
bring awareness to the western speak
about it all the time yeah speak about
it tweet about it go on social media
talk about it one person can't do it but
if we all
uh pitch in it's gonna happen it's gonna
happen write articles make videos tweet
about it go to facebook go to instagram
and talk about this if everybody starts
doing it the whole
scenario will change so that's what
needs to happen right thank you very
much numbers
yes all right nice meeting you good
questions
thank you bye
yeah
okay let's bring in uh leo good evening
good day
hello
hello professor
okay
uh good evening professor hello
yeah i am from shanghai and i have a
question for you
uh
[Music]
so
i have been really i have really
uh i have been really keen to know this
and i have tried to get your attention
to this topic i want to ask you why
india and china have differences when we
never had them historically before
indian dependence
china
india and china share
a lot of cultural similarities we
have both co-existed as center of powers
for a long time during ancient times and
without any
animosity i have personally visited
saint xindui area which shows how
advanced chinese civilization
was at one uh was once upon a time
yeah very good question and i'm glad you
bring this up so if you look at the
history of china it's at least three and
a half thousand years old right as you
must be very very much aware
and india and china we have had cultural
trade etc relations for around 2000
years
for around 2000 years i think i'm going
to mute you because
yeah okay so we have had this
relationship for a very long time we
have never ever been enemies we have
always
been friends very friendly relations
you've had chinese uh
travelers coming to india indian
travelers going to china it's always
been that way what's happened in the
last 60 years or so is after the chinese
annexation of tibet which happened in 19
in the early 1950s india and china for
the first time had a common boundary
account border and that border was not
demarcated it's never been demarcated so
uh that is essentially the root of all
the problems the long and demarcated
boundary and for some reason it's never
been agreed upon so the the two
countries keep having all these multiple
rounds of talks about the boundary issue
but it's never moving forward it's never
been settled and that essentially is the
root cause of the problem that we see
today the india in china or india and
tibet border which is undemarcaded so we
have differing claims and then the
soldiers keep going around and tussling
and
having all these little clashes and that
just keeps the tensions rising so that
is the root cause of the issues that we
are seeing today but for the longest
part of history india and china have
never ever been rivals so that's what i
can offer you
today but for the longest part of
history india and china have never ever
been rivaled
but for the longest
okay so
what's the solution according to you
the solution is to demarcate the
boundary and become
yeah the the boundary problem is the
only problem
if if the boundary can be demarcated
for both the sides according to both
sides satisfaction then the problem goes
away
so that's the solution
both countries need to work on that
all right
okay i got it thank you
nice meeting you thank you
bye
okay let's bring in somebody else uh let
us bring in
let us bring in mr
pushkar
hello hello sir
and i am
am i audible
yes you are audible sir where are you
from
sir i'm from
okay
what's your question
uh sir my question is about dictatorship
in india
so as you told that uh the western
countries they put up dictators in
africa to serve their national interests
so why did they let india be democratic
why didn't they
ask nanu to become a dictator in india
and
make india dictatorship as you see that
uh stranger gandhi he imposed emergency
on india and after mr indra mrs indira
gandhi called then any prime minister
didn't impose emergency on india and try
to become without western health
so what's your views on this
okay very good question very good
question so you know what you know what
is the best form of dictatorship
the best form of dictatorship is a
dictatorship that looks like a democracy
when you have only one party that keeps
getting elected again and again and
again and if you have only one set of
people who are ruling you for 30 40 50
60 years
that is the best form of dictatorship it
looks like a democracy it functions like
a democracy you have elections and yet
you have the same people getting elected
all over again over and over so that's
how india functioned until now until
very recently
india is now making a transition to a
more democratic country
india is still not a proper full
democracy because there are so many
other problems so that's why
so you see what the british did is when
they left india they installed a set of
people who carried on the legacy of the
british
india is still governed as if it is
under british occupation
we have the same laws we have a
constitution that has its roots in the
1935 act which the british passed
and all the institutions of india are
still acting as if they're british
institutions the institutions have never
been reformed so we are essentially
still under in in a way under under
foreign occupation under foreign rule so
that is the perfect scenario you don't
need to put a saddam hussein kind of
person when you can have this sort of
drama going on right
so that's what happened
that's what that means to say that 50 60
years elections were manipulated
no no no no no it is not
it's a good question again they were not
men i mean i mean i don't know if they
were manipulated but the people were so
brainwashed into believing this freedom
struggle nonsense that we got freedom
without any violence and we should we
owe everything to the congress party
that the people themselves happily kept
on voting again and again for the same
party and you keep them illiterate you
keep them uneducated you keep them poor
and then you position yourself as the
only savior they will keep voting for
you it's only today with social media
that people are seeing the reality and
now that party is no longer in power
so now things are changing and now
that's why you see so much opposition to
india in the western media because that
structure is falling
you see that's how it works
thank you sir all right nice meeting you
nice meeting you thank you
yeah
okay let us bring in
whom shall i bring in let's bring in mr
anand
hello hello sir namaskar
namaskar namaskar how are you doing
where are you from
uh sir i'm from ujj madhya pradesh
how are you nice to meet you i'm very
well i'm very well what's your question
sir sir my question is that uh
around the start of 20th century
uh there were three spiritual gurus that
were present in india sai baba swami
vivekananda and uh
and sir as we have read and heard
that they have made huge contributions
towards the society and
their contributions abroad also and have
established a good image
of india
so sir my question here is that uh if
they had those immense powers uh or for
the lack of a better whatever i would
say special or superpowers
so sir uh could it have made a
difference if they had made their
contribution being in india towards the
freedom struggle also
because it's never
discussed about that they have made
their contribution in freedom struggle
or anything like this
okay uh so good good question right so
we're you're saying there were three
three spiritual gurus swami vivekananda
cyber and who's the third one the
paramedics
right so you're saying this yeah so so
first of all i don't know if they had
superpowers like they could fly or have
magic but yes they had very immense
spiritual attainments that is what is uh
understood about them they were very
very um
highly accomplished spiritually yes
that's what i what what is understood
about these three uh great people so
your question is why did they not
contribute to the freedom struggle it's
because see everybody has certain
aptitudes and certain strengths now i
may be a good scientist it doesn't mean
i'll be a good cricketer or a good
footballer i may not be be a good uh
something else right and similarly if
somebody is spiritually very advanced it
doesn't mean that they'll be able to
contribute in every field
a person who is a wonderfully
accomplished spiritual guru may not be a
great footballer or a great politician
or a great scientist
right everybody especially somebody who
has such incredible
advance attainments
in a certain field it takes a lifetime
of discipline and dedication to reach
that stage and you have to focus only on
one field
and then you can
help people you can teach people things
but you may not be able to get involved
in politics politics is a very dirty
game and the freedom struggle it was all
politics there was no freedom struggle
there it was all satyagraha and all this
make-believe struggle there was no
actual um
a real freedom struggle involves
violence you have to throw out the
foreign occupier and kick them out
against their will that is a real
freedom struggle india never had a
freedom struggle
and the real freedom fighters are the
ones who were jailed who were hanged
were killed on the streets and their
names are not remembered so it's a very
different thing and so that's what i can
say see a person who is a spiritually
accomplished person may not be able to
become a great politician or something
else in a different field and that's why
they i
they could from their perspective from
from their in
in whatever manner they could that's
what i can say
thank you sir thank you for choosing all
right
thanks for watching
okay let us bring in somebody else let's
bring in mr ishan who's been waiting for
quite some time
hello hello
hello how are you doing where are you
from sir
from milky way
from the milky way that's a fantastic
answer i've seen you before right yes
what's your question sir
yes sir so i had a question
so
you spoken about books like
the art of walk
so i wanted to ask you how do you read
these books
how do you establish the discipline to
read this book because i
because i've seen it that especially
indians they
their mind tends to you know be like
fast fast let's you know read it
fast and more faster i just want to
finish it you know they get overwhelmed
so how do you establish the discipline
to
read such books and how do you read them
what's the technique
yes that's a very good question how to
learn something and how to be
disciplined in in reading books so first
of all i have never had to discipline
myself to read books i have always been
interested in knowledge and i have
always been driven by my curiosity so if
you ask me to read a book on something i
don't i don't find interesting i will
not have the discipline to read it i can
only read stuff that i find interesting
so if my curiosity takes me to that
place then i will not need discipline to
to read the book so that's the first
thing now how do i actually read a book
like for instance
it's a very large book how do i read it
so i give myself permission to forget
everything i read i'm going to read it
and i'm not going to try and memorize
things underline things read this
paragraph three times no i'll just read
it i read quite fast so i give myself
the permission to forget everything and
i know that if i have that permission
then the things that i find especially
interesting i will i will retain that so
it is something so for instance the
arthashastra if you read it five times
you will
learn new things every time
so that's how i do it i don't retain
everything 100 when i read something i
may return 20
or 30 at most in one reading
then i will revisit it so it takes time
it's not something you can do in a week
a book like the eartha shasta it may
take you maybe five years ten years to
master it which is a very huge amount of
time from your perspective right so it's
like that see learning is a lifelong
process it's not like by the time you're
18 or 20 you have to learn everything
and then you go and live your life no
learning is a lifelong process so i
allow myself to be led and driven by my
curiosity i don't even try to read a
book in its entirety i may find some
chapter interesting i'll read this
chapter right now then i'll put it away
and later i may revisit it at a later
time so that's how i do it there are so
many books i have read only some part of
it maybe one third one a half or
something i never try force myself to
complete a book
if it is no longer interesting after
five chapters i throw it away i mean i
throw it i mean i just keep it aside and
that's how i do it so that is the way i
read and that's how i've always been and
that's that's worked for me it may not
work for everybody but i can offer you
my perspective right
all right sir
yes sir just one more suggestion
suggestion yes sir what's the suggestion
yes i think i don't know if you remember
but i think in the first session when i
first came here i told you
to make something on automatic mark so
since the podcast between auto one
bismarck
authored
okay so since the podcast is here can
you
you know sometime in the future you know
just
invite some person who has gone deep
into his life
what a great suggestion
very good suggestion i will certainly
try and do that
thank you
amazing
yeah
just one more yes that's it that's it
that's it that's it okay tell me what is
the one more thing tell me
is this a question
no it's not a question
so i was just thinking that can you
invite him and you know
who exactly who is it
okay i will look him up and let's see
yeah thanks for the suggestion thank you
bye
all right um
as always we have lots of people
waiting in the queue so let's bring in
mr um
mr kabir bisla hello
hello hello how are you doing where are
you from sir
it's a mirror sir
merit yes okay what's your question
yes sir so my question is
yes sir uh you have you have done your
podcast with anushda
and sir from there you concluded that he
was alive till 85
and okay yeah he didn't come out because
uh
the
sanctions
british so sir i want to ask sir even
after his death why are they not
revealing that is to
identity uh after his death why are they
not revealing his true identity that's a
good question i i think uh what anuj dar
said is that
the entire uh story of the so-called
independent struggle is based upon a lie
they have elevated the stature of mr
muhammad as gandhi to the high heavens
and now if
if the truth about sabah shandra bose is
revealed
then the entire investment these people
have done in the in building up the
image of mandalas gandhi will kind of uh
be wasted
because people will realize the
contributions the real contributions of
nita sabach and rabos and they will
realize what mr khan did and so on so
forth so that is the reason just to
protect the image of mr gandhi
and of course we we know that the
government invests a lot of effort a lot
of time energy in propping up the image
of mr gandhi all the swachh
bharathabiyan and all everything is
based upon the image of mr gandhi right
they're using mr gandhi to to as the
logo and the mascot for all of these
things
and if
a different kind of truth comes out then
that entire investment will be in vain
so that is the argument i believe mr
anujar has made so i am still in the
process of reading the book so i have
yet to draw uh concrete conclusions but
i think that is the uh what was
discussed on that day in our podcast and
i think it's it's quite plausible
whatever what he is saying
yes thank you all right thank you
nice meeting you again
okay let's bring in
someone who's been waiting for a while
who is there
uh let's bring in mr
sharma
hello i said
big fan of you
thank you so much nice meeting you
thank you thank you very much my
uh i am from
bemidja yeah
okay okay my first question is how we
can revive uh sanskrit language and how
hebrew was revived
what are the challenges faced by hebrew
to revive it
right so that's a very good question
yes sir
that's my question how we can
we can revive sanskrit and what are the
challenges
in this journey
all right so let's talk about hebrew so
the the hebrew language was not in use
for a very long time it's an ancient
language it's the original language of
the of the jewish people now the jewish
people were
uh scattered across eurasia mostly in
europe for a very long time and for over
a thousand years the hebrew language was
not unused
not in use they spoke languages like
yiddish etc that had some
elements of the hebrew hebrew vocabulary
etc but it was mixed up with other
languages like german and so on and so
forth
so when the nation was
of israel was created in the 1940s then
the jewish people their government
decided to revive hebrew and they made
the teaching of hebrew compulsory
in all the schools classrooms and they
made it the medium of education so just
in 10 20 years it was very easy to bring
hebrew back and make it a living
language again and now all the official
communications
all the news all the media everything is
in hebrew so it took it's it's not
something you can do next week or next
month it takes 10 20 years and israel is
a small country so the challenges were
less and there was very little
opposition to reviving hebrew in israel
when it comes to india india is a deeply
fragmented country we are still deeply
colonized if you say we're going to
revive sanskrit then all kinds of people
will rise up against india rise up
against this
this endeavor so it the challenge is
much larger in india because uh the
education system has created this
attitude among everybody who gets
educated that india is a backward
culture in sanskrit is the language of
operation and all that nonsense it is
being officially taught in our education
system they are brainwashing all the
kids all the youngsters so that is a big
challenge so how do you bring back
sanskrit you need a strong you need a
strong enough leader who will do it
despite the opposition that's the first
thing and secondly make it compulsory in
in education make sanskrit the official
language in education start one year at
a time start from next year's
kindergarten kg then junior kg then
senior kg then over 20 years you can
extend it to all levels of the education
system so it has to be a phased
phase deployment and of course uh
it it will face opposition but if you
have a strong enough leadership it is
certainly possible so i would say that
it would take about 20 30 years
at most to bring back sanskrit into the
mainstream it would not take long it's
not a dead language for thousands of
years for instance until the 19th
century it was the official language it
was the medium of education in schools
and temples across the country
everywhere also the british who
destroyed the education system of india
and they wiped out
what are they sanctuary
sir if our receive munis were farsighted
so they must have protected our
text for one question per person
one question proposal i think it's very
clear i made it very clear only one
question proposed right sorry all right
so thank you for the question and maybe
next time you can ask another one yeah
right i am waiting all right so long
for everybody
nice meeting you very good question
thank you thank you bye
all right
let's bring in mr pawan
hello
hi sir
namaste how are you
very nice what's your question sir
sir who was uh uh ruling before nandas
we know india is an ancient civilization
but uh i think recorded history says uh
it seems like nandas were the first
empire but
who's actually ruling before nanda's
maybe before magadha empire
a very good question and i don't
have an accurate answer uh we know that
see
uh if you look at india's history
textbooks if you look at writers from
the past like rc majumdar
i think the nanda dynasty is considered
to be where indian history officially
begins because before that the records
are not very clear or whatever and
because the british had to compress
indian history into a certain timeframe
that's why everything seems to start
with the nanda dynasty and the mauryan
dynasty the time of the buddha etc
but of course there was much more before
that but we don't have the details so
even i don't have a clear idea
of exactly who was there before the
nanda dynasty so the nanda dynasty was
in magadh that is bihar and
that region bihar bengal orissa that
region
i am not quite sure that's a very good
question you've asked and unfortunately
i
i can't think of who was ruling that
region before the nanda obviously
somebody must be doing it
i think i will have to look it up and i
will have to
answer that question enough in a future
episode but you've brought out a very
good question i'm not sure we have the
answers but i think i need to look that
up
that's what i can say
all right sir
thank you for the question
thank you yeah thank you
very nice meeting you very nice meeting
you thank you so please don't stop
certainly thank you so much
okay let's bring in whom shall we bring
in let's bring in mr guru
hello
hi hello
hi
where does it start
can we break the cycle and view it in a
third person's perspective
okay good question i have never seen any
evidence of cyclical time
i know certain very eminent etc writers
etc talk about cyclical time i've even
read the papers they try to introduce a
certain kind of differential equation a
very complicated convoluted differential
equation to say that time is cyclic see
i'm a simple person i look at i i see
time from a physics perspective and from
the perspective of physics we don't
quite know what time is of course we use
the time variable in our equations and
all that
and if you look at the entire
the entire known history of the universe
if you look at the
best theory that we have
of the history of the universe which is
the so-called big bang theory the
standard model all that time begins 13.8
billion years before today which is the
the event which is known as the big bang
which is actually the expansion of space
time from a very small
from essentially what looks like was a
singularity and from that time has
flowed in one direction now we don't
quite know what time is time is very
mysterious it's still not understood
at all
but from everything we know from a
physics perspective time is only flown
in one direction of course the equations
are bi-linear they can go back in time
also and that's why we were able to
trace back what could have happened in
the beginning so that's what i can say i
have never seen any evidence i mean i
don't know what on what basis people
claim that time is
cyclical
uh when they bring in philosophical and
spiritual concepts into physics it's no
longer physics
so from my perspective i can only say
that time is linear i have seen no we
have the theory of the yogurts and all
that is not cyclical time
that is simply history repeating itself
so that is not
the the
idea of cyclical time the time itself is
cyclical historical events follow cycles
that is true but that is not cyclical
time there is just human history that
that has patterns that repeat itself
that you of course see that
so from my perspective from a physics
perspective i have seen no evidence
whatsoever for cyclical time i know some
people talk about that there's a big
following also but no i i
i go on the basis of evidence and there
is no evidence for that so that's what i
can tell you
so we can think that so can we say that
uh historical events repeating
themselves as
sorry i didn't get you could repeat that
so means if something in history is
repeating again so people are calling it
a cycle of time coming again i am not
sure if that's what they call cycle of
time i don't get their arguments their
arguments don't really make a lot of
sense to me i regret to say that but uh
from the perspective of physics from the
perspective perspective of science time
is just time it doesn't go in cycles
unless there is a cyclic universe of
which we have no evidence so that's what
i can tell you
all right sir
thank you sir thank you thank you nice
meeting you
have a good day bye
thank you bye
okay
let us bring in
mr pranav
hello
so my question is uh what happened with
the buddhists of bihar after the
invasion took place like we know like
buddhism was the majority religion of
bihar before the turkic invasion
but uh like buddhism just got
disappeared and like how hinduism became
one of the major religion here and
buddhism just got disappeared
okay very good question
so firstly there is no difference
between buddhism and hinduism just like
there is no difference between the
between the between the vedanta
philosophy see the differences are very
very very small very minuscule and those
tiny two percent differences have been
blown out of proportion and that's what
has been used by the british and the
foreign colonizers to create these
divisions in indian society buddhism
hinduism jainism these are all under the
dharmic umbrella they're all part of
dharma and that's what i would say first
of all so so see hinduism buddhism these
are foreign concepts it's just dharma
and dharma comes in a variety of flavors
and all that right so these are not
separate religions it's not religion
first of all really religion means one
book one prophet and one god
we don't follow that
right so now what happened to buddhism
is the question because that particular
flavor or variety of dharma was
prevalent at different points in time in
various parts of india like you say in
magadha in the bihar region etc in
patliputra and so on you had
what would you would call buddhism was
prevalent at the time for instance if
you look at the university of nalanda
it is portrayed as a buddhist university
but you know what they were teaching
everything they are including the four
vedas but historians want to portray in
a certain light now when you talk about
the demise of what we call buddhism the
turks they came from central asia right
now before the turks took over central
asia the entire region of central asia
was dharmic and you had what we call
buddhism all over the place in in the
entirety of central asia in hinduism
also for instance if you go to even if
you if you go to uh
armenia you find remains of hindu
temples there and all across central
asia turkmenistan tajikistan and so on
so forth you find the destroyed remains
of buddhist stupas everywhere and who
destroyed it these turks did that so
they had this great uh zeal
to destroy statues of the buddha and to
destroy everything that looked like
buddhism and they called these statues
these murtis they called them both
because it was buddha they only sought
statute of buddha across central asia so
when they finally
invaded india and occupied parts of
india they went after every single
representation of buddha
they wanted to destroy every
representation of buddha they could find
and that's why they went after buddhism
and that's how buddhism or or the
both the dharma part of dharma was
completely eradicated from india it was
not brahmin so did that or hindus who
did that it is the turks who did that
they destroyed every single buddhist
statute
you will not find a single structure of
the buddha in india whose head is still
on the shoulders they are all headless
it's the turks i have seen this i have
seen those i have seen those
yes and they did not even they did not
stop at simply beheading the statues
they beheaded all the teachers all the
monks everybody so that's why the living
memory of buddhism of both dharma was
wiped out from india by the turks so
that is what happened all right and so
uh i have just a related question from
this
like why dharma got eradicated from
indonesia and southeast asia but not
from india that's a whole different
story that's a whole different story i
will take one question per person so
we'll stop
okay
uh let's bring in mr aloof
that's a lot of noise
okay
okay then i'm gonna i'm gonna bring you
back later sorry very sorry uh let's
bring in somebody else
um let's bring in mr amit
hello
hello sir
hello sir big fan
thank you so much very sir
i'm from west upc right now i'm here in
bangalore
all right and
first of all i just wanted to
congratulate you
um
you've uh
you've brought back this discussion on
indic revival and folks like us we're
falling in love with our culture again
and it's all thanks to people like you
so my question
is
so there's a lot of discussion
um around changes in curriculum and
education system that we need
and
we know right now
uh right from the beginning we are
taught that
we are taught all about our uh
all about uh how we how we've been
um
how we've been uh
so my question is how will that change
basically come about
like will the government have to do it
will they have to
um
change something in the constitution
make some laws or should we do something
about it
like
basically start from our homes
and that will uh bring about that change
so you are asking how do we change the
education system how do we change the
curriculum i think that is entirely in
the hands of the government because the
government controls the curriculum the
government controls everything the ugc
etc and so on so forth so they have come
up with a new education policy which is
like
much
more of the same actually
some small changes structural changes
here and there but it's not really a big
change
so what needs to happen is uh
the education system is entirely
controlled by the government of india so
it is only they who can change the
system the structure the textbooks and
whatever else right so they have to do
it but today what we are finding is the
education is that the education system
is quickly
in the next 10 20 years at most it's
going to become quite irrelevant because
the degrees that they are offering they
have no actual real world use in the
21st century they're giving these ms in
english literature and god knows what's
silly what um msc in home science and
god knows what silly courses still exist
19th century courses they're still
giving them out you know what they these
courses don't give you any any real
skills that you can use in the 21st
century to get a job and to to make a
difference in the world
so increasingly what you will find is
that these courses will go out of either
go out of existence or they'll become so
irrelevant that people will not take
them
and what you will find is people will
start acquiring skills and online
certifications or whatever to
demonstrate you have the skills and you
can use them so that is another avenue
by which the education system will
become relevant and as you can see
you can get almost any kind of knowledge
for free online today so people who are
driven by curiosity who want to gain the
real knowledge about their past about
their heritage they will start finding
it online
so that's two ways either the government
does it or the people will seek it out
on their own but unfortunately the
education system is still something kids
have to go through and that has this
brainwashing effect in which they start
hating their own culture and feel
ashamed of their own culture for that i
have been saying for a very long time
the government needs to take steps
maybe they feel it's not still the right
time for that they will wake up wait
another ten year years or so i don't
know i don't know what they're doing i'm
not privy to what their plans are so
that's just what i can say
that's where we are today
all right sir i'll just finish by uh
saying that i'm a computer engineer and
i love the content you put out
especially that
that talk that you did with dr shibash i
absolutely loved it sir thanks a lot sir
thank you thank you so much nice meeting
you
okay
um shall i bring in let's bring in mr
prajwal singh
hello
sir
uh
nice meeting you uh
i've been uh waiting for very long
so i'm from uh azamgarh
and my question is regarding technology
so there is a project
my heart is bleeding very fast because
relax relax there's no need to be tense
not at all relax
so uh yeah
the technology that uh
what are your thoughts upon meta verbs
like mark zuckerberg's
new project
yes the metaverse that's what everyone
is talking about so the metaphors is
going to be this augmented reality kind
of thing in which you will have
holograms people
representations of people in holographic
form sitting in the same room as you as
you even though they are in a different
continent that sort of thing and you are
going to have a reality that is
augmented so you're gonna be living in
a virtual world that kind of
is uh
is in addition to the real world that we
live in and that sort of thing a
cryptocurrency will play a big role in
that so that's the kind of uh thing they
are trying to create they have renamed
facebook to meta that's what mark
zuckerberg has done and there's a
there's a huge amount of investment
that's happening in that
so it is expected that over the next 10
years
the entire technology will change and we
will increasingly be living
a mixed kind of life half of it will be
real half of it will be in the cyber
cyber universe and that sort of thing so
that's what the metaverse is is going to
be like that's what they're trying to
create there's gonna be a whole economy
built around that
uh like i said cryptocurrency would be a
very big component of that and you will
have virtual real estate in the
metaverse which you can buy and sell
and you can do all kinds of things in
that and that's what it's like so let's
see how it goes it looks like that's a
very big
part of the future whether we like it or
not the world is going to be like that
uh is it going to be good for us bad for
us only time will tell but that is the
direction the world is certainly it
certainly seems to be going towards
so
does it carries a lot of cons as well
because a lot of people
portray it uh in negative light that
it's
it's kind of negative evolution for
social media
so what what is what
so what they're saying is that they
smoke essentially
uh cut off our connection with the real
world we will try and always be in this
make-believe artificial world and it's
like an addiction of kind of some sort
right in the past people used to get
addicted to drugs and all that opium or
whatnot and today they will all spend
their entire time
in this imaginary
uh virtual world they will
stop exercising stop going out stop
socializing and all that so yes there
are certainly a big drawbacks to this
sort of thing
but there's big money being poured into
it so yeah
it could certainly very much
happen and be the shape of tomorrow
so let's see how it goes uh
there are pros and cons to everything
there seems to be a lot of cons like you
said but that's just the way the world
is it's about capitalism it's about
making money
yeah a lot of
power will be transferred to just one
person so it's a yeah
so that was it
nice meeting all right thank you so much
nice to have you guys
thank you nice meeting you mike
all right let's bring in mr utkarsh
hello
uh sir i have been hoping to ask you uh
regarding
uh hello yes uh i'm i'm living in china
and i'm from new delhi
hello okay uh so sir i have been hoping
to ask you like is communism the problem
or is just
america the problem
or is this the implementation of women
isn't the problem secondly uh
this is an extension to my question like
i think uh if america was actually
concerned about human rights vigors or
tibetans
in any case like why are they not
concerned about the same
people who are living in like there was
a ravanan genocide
in africa there has been genocides in
different parts of the world where
america never intervened directly but
where they see their profit they just
intervene so are we being played
are india and china being played is this
the new great game where we are just
being played like india is the only
massive economy a massive country that
can counter china in all of asia so do
you think we are just being played by us
or are they really concerned about
democracy
just okay i just just shed some light on
it
see democracy is just a pretext it is
something they use when it's convenient
for them to they use it as a stick to
beat other countries with they also
bring out the issue of human rights
whatever it suits them
if we look at history at historical
records you will see that this country
the united states has itself done all
kinds of human rights abuses i don't
think that's a controversial topic it's
all part it's all a part of the
historical record you can look up
there's massive amounts of literature
that that corroborates
this so the us
it uses human rights as a stick to beat
certain countries with when it's
convenient for them they talk about
democracy but look at the certain
countries they support like saudi arabia
is there a democracy it's not a
democracy but they're perfectly happy to
be in bed with them so it's all about
convenience the u.s after all at the end
of the day is concerned with its
long-term national interest they want to
retain their hegemony all over the
across the world they are the only
superpower in the world as of today
they are the only country that controls
the global economy that has the their
currency is the global reserve currency
and they are the only country that has
military bases all across the world no
other country has that and they want to
retain this superpower status is it's
essentially an imperial system
and certainly they will want to play one
country against the other
right now the chinese are rising their
ambition is to displace the u.s and
replace them as the superpower as the
sole superpower by 2050 or something
like that right so the u.s perceive
china as a big threat and
for now they will use india as as a
bulwark against china
but if india becomes too big again in
the future they will have the same
attitude towards india also so it's all
from the u.s perspective it's all about
retaining their germanic position
nothing else nothing that matters
so in some sense india and china are
being played but the chinese also have
the same ambitions they also have the
hegemonic ambitions and they want to
replace the us so the chinese are also
a similar kind of nation they are also
currently showing this imperialist
tendency they are bullying all their
neighbors all the asian nations so it
makes sense as of today for india and
the us and the quad countries and
everybody else to band together and
contain china but in geopolitics there
are no permanent friendships there are
no permanent alliances there are no
permanent adversarial
relationships it's all about what's
convenient
right now
so for india from india's perspective
india has to build up its economy its
military power and hopefully india will
be the superpower in which case the
world i think will be a better place
because india doesn't have that
expansionist imperialist culture so
that's what i would say
thank you sir thank you sir
thank you nice meeting you good question
thank you sir
okay let us bring in sejal matri
hello
uh hello sir
hello hi hi from now i have
uh i'm from mumbai
and i'm a law student suddenly pursuing
law so i have this question uh about
radiatives so i have some uh i have
searched a lot about radiatives like uh
if you talk about the present government
even a slightly small controversy is
blown out of so much proportion but uh
such a major controversy like radiatives
i did not see any information on the
internet
or not or not there was any such
discussion at that time as well
right that's a very interesting point
yeah so i want to know like where we can
get information about the same and why
isn't there much talk about this
yeah i don't know where you would get
information about the radio tapes i've
never tried to look for it of course i'm
aware of the entire issue where all
these so-called journalists they were
acting as power brokers on behalf of the
then
ruling regime in india which is the
congress party so what this tells you
is that see like you said that incident
they tried to downplay it
and they tried to not report about it at
all and today if any little thing
happens they will make a big human cry
about everything that they can twist and
portray as the government not doing
things right
so what it tells you is that the media
is has never been free it's never been a
free impartial media they have worked as
agents of the ruling power it's always
been that way and that is not something
you will only find in india it's you
what you will find anywhere in the world
look at the united states i will not
take names but various media companies
etc they have their own political
agendas and they have their own various
masters that they have to serve
so the media
we have to wait we today we are waking
up and finding out that the media is has
never been free the media has never
reported things impartially they see the
media is a business
they have sources of funding and when
you have somebody who's funding you
you're gonna have to do what they tell
you to do
right
and who has the most money in the
country it's various political parties
and various intermediaries who can
funnel that money into various media
organizations so i am not saying that
all media organizations are like this
and i'm not saying that all politicians
are doing this but one could safely
assume that overall there's a high
probability that any media company any
reporter could possibly have some such
motivations so that explains why
historically india's media has served a
certain political party all of them
that's why they try to downplay whatever
happened all that
all those revelations that were leaked
out and that's why today they're trying
to portray everything the current
government does as bad
that's
the way the game is played
all right thank you
thank you good question thank you bye
okay
uh
let's bring in mr krishna
hello sir
good evening namaste
namaste
like uh two weeks ago
i i think you look familiar yes must be
yes yeah yeah we did me together what's
your question it's a question
my question is that
uh there is a thing that most of our
ancient knowledge is which uh what we
had during our past most of them have
been uh either destroyed
and uh they have been transported to the
european nations due to the colonial era
and those vedic knowledges and what we
what the knowledge is that we had during
those time were used uh by the europeans
for their advantages and the development
what they are what we are seeing today
um in the europe and the foreign nations
are mostly due to our vedic knowledges
uh like uh medicines uh making of metals
and so on so uh
how what are the knowledge is what they
have gained from here and used there for
other than uh industrial revolution
shark and that the
metallurgy and so on what are the
knowledges what they have looted from
here and used there and
which is the total basis of the
technological investment
all right so i could i could make the
claim with
a reasonable amount of uh
confidence that most of
modern science that we have today
is built upon the found a foundation of
ancient
indian science and knowledge so for
instance all of the mathematics
that was developed in the in europe in
the
during the scientific revolution etc it
was all based upon
information that was taken out of india
for instance calculus trigonometry
algebra
and much more the the various uh
all of it you know even the uh decimal
system that went out of india by the
arabs it made its way there and also the
all the knowledge of astronomy
pharmacology toxicology ayurveda event
made its way over there then it was a
repurposed in different ways uh there
was a huge amount of astronomical data
observations that was taken out of india
and it made its way into into europe and
that was the basis of the kepler's laws
the kepler's three laws of planetary
motion and so on and so forth
so everything they were so what they did
was they took this knowledge and they
weaponized it
we did not weaponize it they weaponized
it that's what happened so there's a
whole lot of ancient hindu science that
was taken out of india and it made its
way into europe via the arabic world the
arabs never tried to hide the fact that
this was indian knowledge they they made
it very clear that this is indian
knowledge hindu knowledge but the
europeans they plagiarized it and did
not attribute it to india and that's why
we think everything is it originated in
europe so i have a podcast coming up on
tuesday with dr allah kumar who has
written this book ancient hindu science
so i think you should all
watch that and he goes into more detail
about how this happened and what
knowledge was taken out of india so
that's what i can say in brief that a
huge amount of knowledge was taken out
of india and it is now known as european
knowledge and the entire basis of modern
science is that
so uh the basis of this question is that
uh some most of those uh eventualized or
the people who convert they are claiming
that uh it is the europeans who gave us
information
they will claim it
yeah
it is lies it is all lies right they're
lying
yeah because they are lying through
their teeth like
most of the information are coming from
there we have nothing all of those
contributions that even the languages
are brought from there and they even
claimed that sanskrit was a foreign
language so uh yeah
it's really exciting to see that
that's it so hopefully india is now
slowly waking up and we will see the
truth so it's all about spreading the
knowledge and learning the truth
and you're doing a wonderful job and
you're doing an apprenticeship
thank you so much
all right nice meeting you
thanks
namaste namaste namaste thank you bye
okay let us take one last person for
today i know lots of people are waiting
my apologies i can only take one let's
bring in mr gautam
hello
good evening sir
uh i hope you are fine sir actually i i
have uh one question but two parts to it
um where are you from first of all where
i am from
i'm from modusasa um very nice very nice
okay what's your
um the first part of my question is that
how did string theory fail and the
second part to it is that i was
searching about the
uh new alternative to string theory and
i came across quantum loop gravity
and i didn't quite understand it so i
would like if you shed some light to it
okay what you're talking about is loop
quantum gravity lqg
i think it is very difficult for most
people at any age to understand lqg it
is so complicated so mathematical uh so
first of all you're saying why how do we
how can we conclude that string theory
has failed
so i
so any
any theory of nature any theory in
physics
need must make
testable falsifiable predictions
right
it must predict some phenomena
it must predict some some new results
and those predictions must be testable
and falsifiable
if a theory does not meet this these
criteria it is not a scientific theory
it's it's a
it's a pseudoscientific theory and
string theory in all these decades has
not been able to make a single testable
falsifiable
prediction
right
and therefore it has failed it gives
rise to 10 race to 500 different
versions of the universe
yes
they call it the string theory
multiverse of the string theory
landscape that is nonsense
there is absolute nonsense a theory
needs to be precise it needs to make
real world predictions in in this
universe right
so his string theory has consumed a lot
of funding a lot of time lot of
careers but it has not made given us any
new predictions of how of what the world
is like and that's why it has failed now
there are many alt proposed alternatives
one of which is
loop quantum gravity so low quantum
gravity is a different kind of thing it
it talks about a certain kind of it says
that that space time originates in these
space-time loops and the interaction
intersections of the loops they gave
rise to gravity and time also comes out
of it and the smallest unit
of volume
is i think then of the order of 10
raised to minus 99
meters or so i don't remember exactly i
have a short clip about that
on this channel that you can look into
it that you can watch i think i've given
more precise details in that so that's
what lqg is to study it and do that you
need to actually dive deep into physics
so i think you're a little young for
that but maybe in the future you may do
it right yes
yes thank you sir
all right nice meeting you thank you so
much bye
okay ladies and gentlemen i think lots
of people want okay let's bring in one
more person last person for today let's
bring in charmi hello
hello sir how are you
i'm very well how are you doing
i'm very well thank you um thank you for
taking my question uh you're from
australia
yeah
not today sir today i'm in india
you're in india welcome back home madam
thank you thank you sir
uh okay
so like my question is um
like we see there's a lot of
neo hinduism uh coming up like you know
lots of gurus and babas and they often
come up with like you know nice um
uh
like it's in a way i find it it's it's
good also that like that way like we get
a lot of interest from youngsters or
even from uh
probably um foreigners
but it's actually
is it really good because just if you
allow me to elaborate a little bit like
you know you just
have a good yoga is branded is known
hindu and um like sometimes i mean maybe
it's just to attract uh foreigners or
other religion people
um but it's also madness like why do we
want to attract foreigners why do we
want to impress them with our culture
when we are not really sure we are we
are kind of like we also don't know what
it is and
you know it so
also confuses so is it really good long
term for india is it really good long
term for dharma i mean very confusing
what do you think very good question
very good question so we have this
proliferation of self-styled gurus
if you have a few thousand dollars and
if you can open a yoga studio then you
can call yourself a guru
so there are all these gurus who have
come up who are cropping up like
mushrooms after the rain and the so the
word guru had a very specific meaning in
the old days before our culture was
wiped out more or less
and today that the term is used very
lightly in a very facile manner so all
these gurus in my opinion are not real
gurus guru was in the old days was a
very highly accomplished person
you needed to put in a lifetime of study
and discipline and education to attain
the status of a real guru before that
you were adiabatic or whatever you know
different levels that you had to rise
through to eventually become a guru and
you would not typically become a guru
until the age of 45 50 or maybe even
more than that today everybody is a guru
and they are interpreting like you said
dharma yoga in a variety of different
ways just in order to make money it's
all capitalism isn't it it's all about
making money and there are some other
people who are trying to draw a more
spiritually inclined audience by giving
themselves various titles
and so on so it's again about getting
funds about getting money it's about
it's all
capitalistic and yes like you so right
like you rightly point out it is in the
long term going to have a very bad
influence and a bad effect on what our
culture is what our dharma is because
now anybody can say that i know what
your dharma is and this is the real
dharma that's what's happening so we
have lost our standards
we what we need is
a standards institute for instance
we india needs to create a yoga
standards institute which will be the
global institute that determines what is
yoga what is not yoga and
that's what needs to happen then we will
be able to standardize things and we
will be able to draw a line between what
is yoga and what is not yoga and
similarly for the various different
dharmic philosophies we need to have
that system instituted and real gurus
need to be put in place so right now
it's like it's a free-for-all situation
there is this individual called vim hof
who has stolen pranayama who has stolen
the uh the the path of the himalayan
yogis who sit in the snow and he has
combined these two things and he calls
it the wim hof method
right so he that is cultural theft that
he is doing and he is making millions
millions of dollars out of it so all
these fake gurus have cropped up and it
is really bad for us so it is for india
to do something about it right now
nothing is happening but i hope in the
future something happens so i'm really
glad you brought this up it's a very
very good question very legit legitimate
concern that you have and i i hope the
government because it's a government
that can set up these institutes we
can't do it we don't have the funding
unless uh 50 or 100 or thousand people
get together in that case
who will
who will decide so the government needs
to take the initiative see that so the
thing is that like it's not even that
it's also like you know uh
we as an indian we have this mentality
to impress like someone with the white
skin no matter what
and yeah it's it's uh
in that like you know we are i mean
obviously all all the other factors are
there like the theft that they are doing
and all but other than that like we are
also like you know we want the approval
from them
i mean
if we really need it you're right all
right i mean
i don't why why should we care if they
like our culture or not like who cares
absolutely absolutely see the the
problem is that over the past a few
centuries we have
we have been portrayed as deeply
inferior to the foreign occupiers and
that's why i think there is a certain
amount of this inferiority complex among
certain indian people many i would say
many indian people that people with
white skin are superior to us so that
needs to slowly be
replaced by a more confident approach as
india will grow economically and power
in military power the the attitudes will
change right now we have this attitude
that we want to impress people from
other countries especially people with
white skin and so on so it is just a
sign of the times that we are living in
hopefully as the years go by things will
improve i am quite optimistic i am very
hopeful
right well that's that's a good thing to
know thank you sir
thank you so much nice talking to you
again thank you bye thank you bye
all right friends ladies gentlemen uh
this brings me to the end of today's
session my apologies to everybody else
who is trying to get in and speak to me
uh we will do more of this and
so thank you all very interesting
session very good questions and i
am as always very grateful for everybody
who comes here who ask questions who
watches thank you so much to all of you
and i will see you in the next ask a
budget session thank you so much